the first thing you have to answer is
what happiness is for you the
most people would just generally be
going through life
without even knowing what they want so
to speak
so you just follow things that make you
feel good
and avoid things that don't make you
feel so good
but that doesn't necessarily mean that
you're following happiness
it's just it's more it's more um you're
just following an
impulse so the first step in in finding
happiness would be to
to to recognize the difference between
just um
going after things that might make you
um
feel pleasant at a time but not
necessarily happy overall and i think
i'm sure
many people are aware of that you know
if you stop and think about it what is
what is it what is it that makes me
happy
you would not necessarily know but you
would know that things that you've been
chasing up to that point are have not
resulted in happiness
and contentment and that's really where
happiness is
um it's not being pleased with the
current experience that you're enjoying
you know with your friends or outdoors
or something
it's more like being uh perpetually
contented which with your own self with
your own
your own well-being uh and that takes
work takes effort it's not just a question of
takes effort it's not just a question of
satisfying your desires
so so recognizing um where the happiness
lies at least the direction where you could
at least the direction where you could
uh where you have a better chance of
finding it
that's already a step towards it so
clarifying for yourself what you really
want what you really need and also like using
what you really need and also like using
your past experiences to see
which one of those actually made you
made you happy in a sense that you were
happy with yourself
content at ease
um so so
uh having uh having a clear picture
about that
is certainly the necessary prerequisite
then probably what
what you will come to realize is that
most common notion
impulse based notion of just chasing
whatever present desire is
it's more often than not not the reason
for happiness
it's uh it it often results in
you know people wanting more people
being unhappy
uh not contented people people pretty
much becoming sort of more driven which is
becoming sort of more driven which is
not a state of uh
ease so in other words chasing
senses although might provide you um
momentary distraction which pleasure you
conflate for happiness
uh you you would pretty quickly realize
that that's not what happiness is rooted
happiness is a state of mind not really
a state of satisfaction of your senses
so most people who would not have
the clear notion of what happiness is
as an experience they would naturally
conflate or getting what i want is what happiness
or getting what i want is what happiness
is
but is this one way of going about it
like not wanting anything that you can
or cannot get
is also another way to be happy so if
you if you don't desire anything
you can't grieve over anything either so
you realize
okay so happiness is a state of mind
that i'm kind of responsible for so you
might not be responsible for
things that you get things that you
don't get things that you had or
then lost things that you lost and then
farm back and so on
but you're certainly responsible uh
for the values that you place upon those
things so whether your values are placed upon
so whether your values are placed upon
getting the objects from my senses side
sounds melted touches having a great
time and so on or do you place the
values on on the
contentment of the mind which often
requires a certain ability to say no to your own
a certain ability to say no to your own
self to draw a line for your own self
because otherwise it will just the
desires will just take you in these
infinite directions or
that you can never satisfy so that's
that's really the
the main key here it's you know how to
find happiness
really should be asked like how to
understand what happiness is and that's
it
if you understand what happiness is even
if you don't make any
excessive direct effort towards it you
will already be
going into that direction because you
have certain clarity for for what it is
so you would already have a clearer
picture as to where to draw line for
your own desires when to say no and so
say you want something
there's already the implicit knowledge
whether that thing is necessary
or it would just be like a satisfaction
of this
insatiable thirst for sensuality or it
would just be a habit
pressure or whatever else and you know
it would probably be better if i were to
say no to myself
it's not a hard thing to guess because
as i said it's all it's it's already
it's already implicit that knowledge so
it's more like when people just
habitually act out of impulse uh
they never notice these things but it's
not you don't you don't require some
some great mental effort and restraint
to start seeing it
and then the more you see it the clearer
it will become
so you will as i said so you will know
where to draw a line
so knowing what happiness is is already
a step forward towards the the right
contentment and so knowing where to when to restrain
and so knowing where to when to restrain
yourself
and then taking responsibility for when
you do allow yourself to engage with
senses and so on that will make the mind
and so on that will make the mind
um well more in your control
so that brings to the second point
knowing what happiness is
is the prerequisite it sets the
direction for for for you to develop a heavy mind
for for for you to develop a heavy mind
and then the development of happy mind
is basically
development of mind that's in your
control not other way around
so the more control you have over your
mind the more ability to withstand it
you have developed the more contented
you are with whatever circumstances life
throws at you
so there will be no um
there will be things would be less
challenging so to speak doesn't mean
everything would go your way but means
that when things don't go your way when
you don't get what you want
you will not lose perspective because
you haven't been blindly habitually
acting out of impulse
at every whimsical desire that your mind
threw at you
so knowing what happiness is and then
developing a certain
um self-control in regard to your own
mind and your own mental state
and that means that's not a magical
thing that that self-control will not
occur as a result of some magical recipe
or something
the the self-control arises on account
of effort that you put in to withstand
the pressure
of your mind and mental desires towards
this so it's that
learning how to draw a line learning how
to say no then enduring it
and and growing out of it so
so happiness is contentment contentment
with yourself
and a degree of self-control
that you have developed will be a degree
of uh
your ability to be happy pretty much
that's uh
it almost corresponds directly